We all want to eat
the kinds of foods
that make us feel
better and live longer.
But there’s so much conflicting
information out there,
so many nutrition opinions.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s my job to give you
the information you need
to make the healthiest
choices possible.
Today we take a close look at the
pros and cons of plant-based eating.
Vegetarian diets and lifestyles
have been shown to reduce the risk
of many chronic diseases,
which now accounts
for the major global burden
of disease,
but the actual direct medical costs
had never been quantified before.
Here's what they found.
The same amount spent
on dental work, but
compared to meat-eaters
who similarly don't
smoke or drink,
or compared to
the general population,
vegetarians had significantly
lower inpatient, outpatient,
and total medical care expenditures,
suggesting more plant-based eating
could be an effective strategy
to save on healthcare costs.
Here's how it broke down.
Significantly lower costs
for chronic lifestyle conditions
such as high blood pressure
and high cholesterol.
This makes sense.
Those eating plant-based diets
centered around whole plant foods
nailed the targets for
cholesterol, triglycerides,
and systolic and diastolic blood
pressure 93% of the time,
97% of the time, 88% of the time,
and 95% of the time, respectively.
Nearly a 50% drop in medical costs
due to depression, too --
that's interesting -- as well as
lower costs across the board.
Cerebrovascular disease
is another name for stroke.
Wasn't there that study that showed
vegetarians had higher stroke risk?
True, but that was before
two subsequent studies found
a lower risk of stroke
with a vegetarian diet,
and not just by a little.
For ischemic stroke, the most
common clotting type of stroke,
vegetarians consistently
had about 60% lower risk.
And for bleeding strokes, about
65% lower risk than nonvegetarian.
And this despite higher homocysteine
due to lower vitamin B12 intake,
which is what may have led
to the higher stroke risk
in the previous study.
Overall, if you do a systematic
review of all the major studies,
a comprehensive meta-analysis
found a significant protective effect
of a vegetarian diet versus
the incidence and/or mortality
from ischemic heart disease
and incidence from total cancer,
with a vegan diet conferring about
twice the reduced risk cancer-wise.
You can also look at it
the other way.
What if you decide to stop eating
vegetarian and start eating meat?
The Adventist Health Study
looked at that and found that
compared to those
who stayed vegetarian,
those who started
eating meat suffered
a 231% increased
risk of gaining weight,
166% increase in the risk
of developing diabetes,
152% increased risk
of having a stroke,
and 146% increased risk of being
diagnosed with heart disease.
And if you keep eating meat,
you may cut your lifespan
by three and a half years.
So better to not just cut out meat,
but cut it out for good.
But it's not all-or-nothing.
Even just cutting down may help.
A food pattern that emphasizes
plant-derived foods was found
to be associated with a
reduced risk of all-cause mortality,
meaning living a
significantly longer life.
So there are multiple benefits
even eating in the direction
of a more plant-based diet,
but what about any risks?
Despite concerns
for protein deficiency,
adequate amounts of protein --
which means 0.8 grams
per kilogram of body weight,
which is about 50 grams a day --
can be consumed in a solely
plant-based diet, as seen among
the other billion plus people around
the world who don't eat meat.
Vitamin B12 deficiency,
on the other hand,
is a very real concern without
a regular reliable source,
and I have videos
on how to do that
either through supplements
or fortified foods.
One benefit you don't hear much
about is the role our diets play
in the emergence of pandemic
infectious diseases,
the subject of one
of my recent books.
It doesn't take much for a virus
to jump from one animal to another,
but there are no examples of plant
viruses ever jumping to humans
for the same reason
we don't ever come down
with a really bad case
of Dutch elm disease.
The largest and oldest association
of nutrition professionals
in the world is clear:
plant-based diets are appropriate
for all stages of the life cycle,
and may actually provide
health benefits for the prevention
and treatment
of certain diseases.
For example, vegetarians and
vegans are at reduced risk
of ischemic heart disease,
type 2 diabetes,
high blood pressure, certain
types of cancers, and obesity.
And to learn more, they encourage
people to go check out
a few good websites.
As the emeritus dean of the School
of Public Health at Loma Linda
once said at a nutrition conference,
"Attitudes toward vegetarian
diets have progressed
from ridicule and skepticism,
to condescending tolerance,
to gradual and sometimes
grudging acceptance,
and finally to acclaim."
In our next story,
we look at how healthier
plant-based diets compare
to unhealthy plant foods and
animal foods for diabetes risk.
In my video on flexitarians,
I talk about how the benefits
of eating a plant-based diet
are not all-or-nothing.
Simple advice to increase
the consumption
of plant-derived foods with
parallel reductions in the
consumption of foods from
animal sources was found to
confer a survival advantage,”
a live-longer advantage.
They call it a pro-vegetarian eating
pattern, just moving in that direction,
as a more gradual, gentle
doable approach.
If you’re dealing with a serious
disease, though, like diabetes,
avoiding some problem foods
completely may be easier
than attempting to moderate their intake.
It’s like clinicians would never tell
alcoholics to simply cut down on alcohol.
Avoiding alcohol entirely
is a more effective and,
ironically, easier for a problem drinker.
Paradoxically, asking patients
to make a large change
may be more effective than
making a slow transition.
Diet studies show that recommending
more significant changes
increases the changes that
patients actually accomplish.
It may help to replace the common
advice, ‘all things in moderation’
with ‘big changes beget big results.’
Success breeds success.
After a few days or weeks of
major dietary changes,
patients are more likely
to see improvements
in weight and blood sugar levels—
improvements that
reinforce the dietary changes.
Furthermore, they may enjoy other health
benefits of plant-based eating.
that may give them further motivation.
Those who choose to eat plant-based
for their health say it’s mostly
for general wellness and disease
prevention, or to improve
their energy levels or immune function.
They felt it gave them a sense
of control over their health,
helps you feel better emotionally,
improves your overall health,
and makes you feel better.
Most felt it was very important for
maintaining their health and well-being.
For the minority that used it
for a specific health problem,
it was mostly for high cholesterol
or weight loss,
followed by high blood pressure
and diabetes, with most
reporting they felt
it helped a great deal.
But others choose plant-based diets
for other reasons like animal welfare
or global warming, and it looks
like they’re more likely to be eating
things like vegan doughnuts,
sugary and fatty foods,
compared to those eating
plant-based because of
religious or health reasons.
I mean the veganist vegan could bake
a cake using soda instead of eggs,
with frosting, covered in marshmallow
fluff and chocolate syrup,
topped with Oreos, with a side of Doritos
dipped in, vegan bacon grease.
But fruit for dessert… in the form of
Pop Tarts and Krispy Kreme pies.
This, is a vegan meal.
Yes, plant-based diets have
been recommended
to reduce the risk of type 2 diabetes.
However, not all plant foods
are necessarily beneficial.
Like in that pro-vegetarian scoring
system you got points for eating
potato chips and French fries,
just because they were technically
plant-based, but Harvard researchers
wanted to examine the association
of not only an overall plant-based diet,
but both healthy and unhealthy versions.
So, they created the same kind
of pro-vegetarian scoring system
weighted towards any sort
of plant-based foods,
and against animal foods and then also
created a healthful plant-based diet index,
where at least some whole
plant foods took precedence
and Coca-Cola was no longer
considered a plant.
Then lastly, they created an
unhealthful plant-based diet index
by assigning positive scores
to processed plant-based junk,
and negative scoring healthier
foods and animal foods.
And then they found that a more
plant-based diet in general was good
for reducing diabetes risk, but eating
especially healthy plant-based foods
did better, nearly
cutting risk in half,
while those eating more
unhealthy plant foods did worse.
Now, but is that because they
were also eating more animal foods?
People often eat burgers
with their fries;
so, they separated out the
effects of healthy plant foods,
less healthy plant foods,
and animal foods.
And healthy plant foods were
protectively associated,
animal foods were
detrimentally associated,
and less healthy plant foods were more
neutral when it came to diabetes risk.
Here’s what the graph looks like:
higher diabetes risk with more and more
animal foods, no protection
whatsoever with junky plant foods,
and lower and lower diabetes risk
associated with more and more
healthy whole plant foods in the diet.
So, they conclude that yes, plant-
based diets are associated with
substantially lower risk of
developing type 2 diabetes,
but it may not be enough to just
lower the intake of animal foods,
but also less healthy
plant foods as well.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.